Berlin Iron Bridge Co. records
Connecticut Historical Society
Berlin Iron Bridge Co. records
1871-1904
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Berlin Iron Bridge Co.
2 linear feet (4 boxes)
Historical Sketch
The history of the Berlin Iron Bridge Company dates back to August 1870 when the company was founded as the Metallic Corrugated Shingle Company. It began issuing stock in July of 1871 and in January of 1873 the name of the company was changed to the Corrugated Metal Company. In March of 1877 Samuel Curtis Wilcox became president and treasurer. In January of 1883 the company changed its name for the final time to the Berlin Iron Bridge Company. In addition to bridges, the company built jail cells, roofs and machine shops.
Samuel Wilcox died in 1886 and vice-president and engineer Charles M. Jarvis became president. Burr K. Field took over as vice-president and treasurer until April of 1890 when Frank Langdon Wilcox (son of Samuel) became treasurer. On October 7th, 1899, the company’s stockholders voted to dissolve the company and the Berlin Iron Bridge Company was sold to the American Bridge Company on May 12th, 1900. Following a lawsuit between the Berlin Iron Bridge Company and the American Iron Bridge Company in a dispute over contract payments, the Berlin Iron Bridge Company was formally dissolved on June 29th, 1905.
Scope and Content
This collection was initially divided into four categories: correspondence, financial papers, stock papers and documents pertaining to the sale of the company to the American Bridge Company. Those four categories have, for the most part, been retained. The bulk of the collection covers the period roughly between 1892 and 1902. The handful of earlier documents, having to do with the Corrugated Metal Company, date back to 1878 and there are also some documents from the period 1903-1905. Some entries in the stock ledger are from 1871.
The collection includes lengthy documentation of the Berlin Iron Company’s tax dealings with the state of New York, its incorporation in Pennsylvania and New Jersey, bills of letting and estimate sheets, bridge contracts, stock increases, lawsuits, and the takeover of the company by the American Bridge Company, as well as the lawsuit between the two companies.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Corporate Names
American Bridge Co.; Corrugated Metal Co.
Subjects
Articles of incorporation.; Construction contracts.; Iron and steel bridges.
Contents:
- I. Records
  - Secretary’s Minutes, 1890-1905 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Corrugated Metal Company Papers, 1878; 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Papers, 1884-1890 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1892-1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1897-1899 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1901-1902; 1903; 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - New York State Tax Papers, 1893-1895 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - New York State Tax Papers, 1896-1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pennsylvania Incorporation, 1893-1901 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - New Jersey Incorporation, 1894-1900 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oscar Reipsame Injury Papers, 1894-1901 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Labor Statistics (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellanous Documents (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Claim Against J.S. Brown, 1896-1901 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brennan Lawsuit, 1899-1904 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mersick Lawsuit, 1900-1902 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bills, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bills, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bills, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellanous Bills; Groton Bills (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Phoenix Bank Documents, 1899-1905 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bills of Letting, 1900 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Estimate Sheets, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Estimate Sheets, January 1900 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Estimate Sheets, February 1900 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Estimate Sheets, March-April, September 1900 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Unidentified Estimate Papers (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Contracts #1125 - #1672 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Contracts #1808 - #1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Contracts #2043 - #2199 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Contracts #2213 - #2787 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Record/Day Book, 1898-1900 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Contracts #2910 - #3032 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Contracts #3144 - #3331 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Contracts #3559 - #3769 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Contracts #4543 - #4840 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Contracts #4853 - #5587 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1887 Stock Increase Papers (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1891 Stock Increase Papers (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1891 Stock Increase Subscriptions (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1891 Stock Increase Agreements (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1895 Stock Increase Papers (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1895 Stock Increase Subscription Receipts (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1895 Stock Increase Agreements (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Undated Stock Charts (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Stock Ledger, 1871-1900 (Box 3, Volume 1)
  - Profit Estimates on Contracts Turned Over to American Bridge (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Charts Related to Contracts Turned Over to American Bridge (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Individual Contract Sheets (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Payments, Materials and Merchandise Sheets (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Agreements and Schedules for Contract Takeover (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellanous Documents Relating to Takeover (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - American Bridge Takeover Documents, 1900-1902 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Bridge Takeover Correspondence, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - American Bridge Takeover Correspondence, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - American Bridge Takeover Correspondence, 1902-1903 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Berlin Iron/American Bridge Settlement, 1900-1901 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - American Bridge Company Lawsuit Documents (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - American Bridge Cash Book (Box 4, Volume 1)